in our last session we talked about
sart's concept of existential
self-awareness and that's the kind of
thing I'm experiencing right now for a
couple of reasons one is that because I
have a sore throat and they caught me
with these cameras just as I was
finishing a throat lozenger
and I'm trying to emulate the
demosthenes like speaking with stones in
my mouth but the second reason why I
feel this existential self-awareness is
that we've come now to the end of this
series
and today's message will be the last in
this series of the consequences of ideas
and what I want to do today
rather than go into detail into several
philosophers or schools of thought that
characterize the day in which we live
now I want to give a sweeping broad
picture of the climate of philosophical
inquiry at the end of the 20th century
there are many schools of thought
competing for Acceptance in our day
but they have several things in common
and all of them in one sense can be
traced back to a movement that was
opposed to kantian movement of the 19th
century
introduced by a philosopher by the name
of August kompt and it was the school
known as positivism
and positivism as it was set forth by
Compton
was an attempt as Marx had given us and
others to
produce a kind of philosophy of History
in which he said in the development The
evolutionary progress of civilization
and of Western Humanity
that people have gone through
three stages of cultural development
and intellectual development that
correspond to stages in human
biological development
and in his analysis he said the first
stage of Western culture is the stage of
its infancy
we're here the dominant themes of
inquiry were those associated with
religion
which according to comp in the final
analysis is nothing more nothing less
than an exercise in mythology
it is an infantile response to our world
and Life to try to make sense of it by
an appeal to some kind of religion
but then as people began to grow up
and as civilization began to mature at
least reaching its adolescence
stage
then the dominant controlling factor to
Define life and the world was found in
the abstract realm of philosophy
but now according to compta at the end
of the 19th century and going into the
20th century
mankind has finally come of age
where we've moved beyond the infantile
and Beyond the Adolescent to the adult
stage
of intellectual inquiry that is
dominated now not by religion or
philosophy but by science
this is a new form of empiricism
and so positivism as it moved into the
20th century and this was developed
particularly by British thinkers such as
AJ air and Anthony flew developed a
concept of of a scientific approach to
reality
by which they came to the conclusion
that no propositions
are meaningful
unless they can be verified empirically
now this is an idea drawn from science
wherein the scientific inquiry in the
Enterprise the data that is collected
and observed have to be tested not by
formal principles or theorems but in the
final analysis their accuracy and Truth
value can only be determined by
empirical
measurement or verification that is if
you can't see it taste it touch it smell
it or so on it isn't real
so that the real is only that which can
be verified by the senses
now not only that but the logical
positivists developed their
law of verification
with respect to meaningful statements or
propositions and the law or principle of
verification simply says
for any statement or proposition to be
meaningful it must be verified
empirically
now this swept through
the philosophical world in the earlier
segments of the 20th century
and It produced in philosophy and in
theology a serious crisis in language
in the 70s and 60s we saw in the realm
of theology the movement called Theo
thanatology or the death of God
and that whole movement the death of God
movement was spawned by a crisis of
skepticism about language and that was
related to the question whether any of
our discussions about God
can be deemed meaningful
or as all religious language simply
emotive
a motive language is language that
expresses feelings
and if we cannot verify empirically the
propositions that we assert with respect
to God that he is eternal that he is
infinite that he is omniscient in all of
these things since we can't see him
subject him to the scrutiny of the
microscope or contain him in a
laboratory for experiments and tests and
so on
then that means that any statements that
we make about God cannot be verified
and if they cannot be verified they
cannot be Laden with meaning
other than emotive meaning
which is to say that what the statements
of theologians like myself are worth is
this that all they really teach is
something about my feeling State
something about my emotions they don't
give us any information or communicate
any objective truth about reality
and so this crisis of God talk burst
onto the scene
after the middle of the 20th century
now of course to the great embarrassment
of the founders of logical positivism it
wasn't too long between between before
the philosophers who were critics of
this system
pointed out what should have been
obvious to the founders of it namely
that their Central thesis
fell by virtue of its own weight
and in the critic critiques that were
launched they revealed that the emperor
had no clothes
because the problem with the law of
verification which states
that the only statements that can be
meaningful are those statements that can
be verified empirically
that's the law
well that law with its statement
cannot be verified empirically
and so as I said it falls of its own
weight and the verification principle
itself fails to meet its own test and if
it fails to meet its own tests it would
have to be seen as a meaningless
statement and if it's a meaningless
statement the whole system then
obviously collapses
now even though the verification
principle met a hasty demise in the
intellectual World some of the basic
tenets of positivistic philosophy
lingered on and maintained a strong
impact on the culture in other ways as
it was linked to other philosophies and
Concepts
again
the Homegrown philosophy of America the
only philosophical movement that was
born
in the continental United States and the
philosophy that many people have said
define American culture in the 20th
century is the philosophy of
pragmatism
formulated by John Dewey and Charles
Pierce
pragmatism
in simple language teaches that the good
or the true is determined not by some
metaphysical Norm or standard which
norms and standards according to
pragmatism remain forever unknowable
remember this was a philosophy born on
this side of the kantian Watershed where
the skepticism remains that we do not
have any access to the realm of
metaphysics to the realm of being that
we are locked in to this side to the
realm of phenomena to the realm of
existence to the realm of positive
things and for the positivist for
example
and its tie-in with pragmatism the
positivists would say and did say
that there is no such thing as truth
only truths
there's no such thing
as value
only values
there's no such thing
as purpose
only purposes
now that may sound crazy to you
How can there be truths unless there is
some Norm or standard by which you
measure a statement to say that it is
true
how can you have truths if there is no
truth how can you have purpose if you
have no purpose well let me say again
here the emphasis is on the particular
rather than the universal on existence
rather than Essence on becoming rather
than being let me Illustrated with my
favorite illustration
of what I experienced in this culture
what I went through
the trauma of sending our firstborn
child our daughter
off to school
for the first time she was going to
kindergarten
when she was five years old and we lived
in Boston
and I knew when she went out the door
that I was now turning over much of her
development
an input of ideas
to somebody outside the family
and so we enrolled her in the public
school system in Boston
and we got a letter a couple weeks later
where we were invited to come to a
parent meeting at the school where the
principal of the school was going to
explain the philosophy of education and
the whole design of the curriculum for
the parents so that we would know what
was going on
and so we wanted this man
began his speech by saying that you
parents I know are concerned about what
your children are learning particularly
those in kindergarten in the earlier
grades your children come home from
school at the end of the day and you say
to them what did you do today and they
say well they played with puzzles or
modeling clay and you say what is this a
sophisticated kind of babysitting
I said I want you to understand
that every single thing that is done
during the course of a school day by
these children has been carefully
thought out and carefully scientifically
designed for a reason
in other words he said there's a purpose
for everything that they do he said for
example from nine o'clock till 9 17 the
kids play with these puzzles and he held
up this puzzle he said you may think
that they're just having fun in gains he
says but these puzzles
were specifically designed and developed
by a team of neurosurgeons from the
Boston general hospital with the
specific purpose in mind in teaching
children how to use their motor skills
in the last three fingers of the left
hand and we gassed and then he said from
9 17 to 9 21 they used this modeling
clay and it has a purpose of developing
this aspect of the child's motor skills
and so on and he went through every
minute of the day and showed why every
single aspect of the day was doing
whatever it was he was doing and at the
end of his lecture after this prodigious
display of technical preparation
he smiled and said are there any
questions
and the immediate response of the of the
audience was spontaneous laughter like
who in the world in their right mind is
going to raise any questions well I
raise money
and I said sir I said I really
appreciate
this presentation and you've made your
point that everything is done here is
done for a purpose
but theoretically you have an infinite
number of individual purposes that you
could choose to implement in the design
of your educational curriculum
and obviously along the way you've had
to make decisions and choices
to include this aspect of learning in
your curriculum
instead of something else
and so you've told us all these specific
purposes that you implement
I'd like you to tell me what the
overarching purpose is
that shapes your philosophical
Educational Theory here
that becomes the norm for why you
implement the specific particular
purposes that you do during the day
I said in other words what kind of a
child
are you trying to produce
and why
when I asked them that question his
immediate response was his face turned
beet red and then Ash White
and he looked at me and he said
I don't know
he said nobody's ever asked me that
question
and I looked at him and I said thank you
so much for your candor I really
appreciate your openness on this
I said but your answer terrifies me
but that's where we are
in the culture
that is the legacy of a positivistic
approach to reality and truth you have
all these purposes
but no purpose
all kinds of particular meanings
but no meaning
no wonder Francis Schaefer stuttered
and raised questions about true truth in
our day
because that's the crisis in modern
philosophy
the crisis is whether there is such a
thing as truth
the pragmatist building on this says
objective truth cannot be known
and you determine the true and the good
and the purposive
by one standard
does it work
I used to visit a country club in
Western Pennsylvania one of the finest
golf clubs in the world Laurel Valley
Country Club and they had an assistant
Pro there named John Rock
and when I would walk into the Pro Shop
John Rock would look at me and he would
never say to me hi RC how are you
his standard greeting that he gave every
time I walked in the door was this
does it work
and I would say yes
and he would say
then use it
he was the quintessential pragmatic golf
instructor
he didn't care about the theory he
didn't care about the form he wants to
know does it work if it works use it
that's the philosophy of pragmatism
where truth
and goodness are determined by what
works
if you have a problem
you solve it now
if your workable solution
creates two new problems
you solve those
and if those Solutions create each two
more
exponentially you just keep chasing them
down and solve them one at a time that's
the American way
the difficult
takes you know we can do immediately The
Impossible will take a little longer but
nevertheless the American Spirit is the
spirit of pragmatism we can make it work
the problem with this however
of being practical or pragmatic
is how do you know if it works
ultimately
pragmatism is really not all that new
pragmatism is concerned with short-term
Solutions
and refuses to think subspecies
eternitatus
from the perspective of the infinite
it came sharply under the critique
of Jesus of Nazareth
who said what if what profit a man
if he gains the whole world
and he loses his own soul
or what can a man give in exchange for
his soul
what Jesus was saying at that point is
if you wanted to work your life on the
basis of what works you better ask
yourself what works ultimately
because it may work well enough to gain
you the whole world but if it costs you
your soul it doesn't work
and it's not good
and it's not true
but that's part of the climate of our
culture
in terms of pragmatism it has other
things that go along with it pluralism
and relativism
pluralism teaches that there is no such
thing as again truth only truths
and that
disparate contradictory truths may be
embraced for the sake of public peace
and fellowship
you have churches today who will give
their ministers optional Creeds to
confess
even though they are antithetical to
each other they say the church is big
enough
to hold within it contradictory
theologies
because we Embrace pluralism
variety
and the Unum of the e pluribus
is exited
it's e pluribus plural now
instead of a Pluribus Unum once you step
into pluralism
or its twin relativism
finally
the perhaps the most dominant school
today in Western philosophy is called
linguistic analysis
or the philosophy of language since the
pursuit of metaphysical truth
and even epistemological truth not to
mention the philosophy of history have
been for the most part abandoned what is
left for students of philosophy and
philosophers to do is to analyze how
people speak and how we use language
one of the most important philosophers
for this in the 20th century was Ludwig
Wittgenstein who said that the meaning
of language is determined in the final
analysis by
customary usage
that his words are not to be defined in
a final analysis by their
etymological derivations or their
historic meanings but rather simply how
they are used and so the task of the
philosopher is to clarify
and to enhance verbal communication
and this comes by an analysis of grammar
of syntax of the structure of statements
determining what kinds of propositions
are used in The Interchange of ideas
and most specifically honing in on the
specific meaning of particular words
and here we are
almost back to square one
where we're examining the tools of
knowledge and the tools of communication
having abandoned
the pursuit of ultimate truth